Guide to the Office of the University Registrar Records, 1853 - 2000
Duke University. University Archives
Office of the University Registrar records 1853 - 2000
Duke University. Office of the University Registrar.
61.5 linear feet, Extent: 31,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
In 1953, Richard L. Tuthill was appointed University Registrar in an effort to centralize the records-keeping processes of the different schools. Broadly stated, the office of the University Registrar had three major responsibilities: 1) admissions, 2) registration, and 3) student records. By 1958, the office of the University Registrar consisted of the Central Records Office and the office of Undergraduate Admissions. Following Tuthill's resignation in 1969, Clark Cahow was appointed Registrar and held the position through 1986. The collection includes grade books from Normal and Trinity Colleges from the years 1853-1926, subject files from the tenures of Tuthill and Cahow, statistical information kept on student admissions, enrollment, and grade performance at Duke University since 1925, the official schedules of courses for semesters and summer school from 1932 to the present, mailings to students from the University, departments, and campus organizations, and microfilmed copies of student transcripts from about 1932 to 1969. The subject files include information on financial aid, the Consortium on Financing Higher Education, university curricula, and the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences. English.
UA.07.09.0002
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Office of the University Registrar Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1971-2000.
Historical Note
The Registrar's position originated in 1899 with Dallas W. Newsom's appointment as Registrar and Recording Secretary to the Board of Trustees. The original position seems to have been largely concerned with financial matters, with the Registrar in charge of the collection of all bills due the College. He shall rent rooms to students, keep the books of the College, and see that all the laws of the Board governing bills due the College should be duly enforced (1903 Bylaws). In fact, Newsom was often listed in the Trinity Catalogues as Registrar and Treasurer. He served in this capacity until 1920.
Apparently, the position was not filled from 1921 to 1953. Though included in the Bylaws of 1936, the office remained vacant. As the University expanded, individual schools had their own registrars or recorders. In 1953, Richard L. Tuthill was appointed University Registrar in an effort to centralize the records-keeping processes of the different schools. Unlike the earlier position, the new registrar coordinated admissions to the University as well. Broadly stated, the office of the University Registrar had three major responsibilities: 1) admissions, 2) registration, and 3) student records, and it concerned itself with the policies, procedures, and decisions relating to each. By 1958, the office of the University Registrar consisted of the Central Records Office and the office of Undergraduate Admissions. The University Registrar oversaw both offices.
Following Tuthill's resignation in 1969, Clark Cahow was appointed Registrar and held the position through 1986. Albert Eldridge (1987-1995) and Bruce Cunningham (1996-) have since served as Registrar.
Collection Overview
The collection includes grade books from Normal and Trinity Colleges from the years 1853-1926, subject files from the tenures of Tuthill and Cahow, statistical information kept on student admissions, enrollment, and grade performance at Duke University since 1925, the official schedules of courses for semesters and summer school from 1932 to the present, mailings to students from the University, departments, and campus organizations, and microfilmed copies of student transcripts from about 1932 to 1969. The subject files include information on financial aid, the Consortium on Financing Higher Education, university curricula, and the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences.
The bulk of the material covers the early 1950s and through the early 1980s, encompassing the tenures of Richard Tuthill and Clark Cahow. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, memoranda, reports, and statistical information. The records reflect the Registrar's current responsibilities for student records and registration, along with former duties concerning student admissions. Two small collections have been incorporated into the record group: 1. Clark Cahow Papers, 1958-1974 (A77-29); 2. University Schedule Committee records, 1970-1982 (A76-188 and A82-92). The Cahow Papers primarily contained records of the office of Registrar. The Schedule Committee seems to have reported directly to the Registrar's office at one time and someone from the Registrar's office served on the Committee.
The records are arranged into the following series:
I. Grade Books, 1853-1926
II. Subject files, 1946-1988
III. Statistics, 1925-
IV. Official Schedule of Courses, 1932-
V. Student mailings, 1987-
VI. Student transcripts (microfilm), c.1939-1969
Subject Headings
Cahow, Clark R.; Consortium on Financing Higher Education (U.S.); Duke University. Academic Council; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Admission; Duke University -- Curricula; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Statistics; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences; Duke University. Office of the University Registrar; Student financial aid administration -- North Carolina -- Durham; Tuthill, Richard Lovejoy
Contents of Collection
- Grade Books, 1853-1859, 1871-1926
  This series contains 42 books with admissions, course, and grade information on students at both Normal and Trinity Colleges. The books are bound, usually large, and at least one page is devoted to each student. The books are arranged chronologically and students are usually listed alphabetically within the books. The first book in the series, 1853-1859, covers grades from Normal College, while the remainder of the material refers to Trinity College. A gap from the years 1888-1898 exists through no evidence has been found as to where those books may be located. The grade book for people who entered Trinity College from 1908 to 1911 is also missing from our collection. This book was probably lost in the 1911 Washington Duke building fire.
  - Grade Book A, Normal College, 1853-1859 (Box 1)
  - Grade Book B, 1871-1872 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book C, 1872 Aug. 19-1872 Oct. 18 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book D, 1873 Jan. (Box 2)
  - Grade Book F, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book E, 1875 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book G, 1874-1875 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book H, 1875-1876 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book [no letter assigned], 1876-1877 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book I, 1877-1878 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book J, 1878-1879 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book K, 1879-1880 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book L, 1880-1881 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book M, 1881-1882 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book N, 1882-1883 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book O, 1883-1884 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book P, 1884-1885 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book Q, 1885-1886 (Box 2)
  - Grade Book R, 1886-1887 (Box 2)
  - Register of Class Grades No. 1, Trinity College, 1899-1900 (Box 3)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 2, Trinity College, Book 2 students entered 1902/03F -1905/06M (letters are the first initial of the last name) 1902-1909 (Box 4)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 3, Trinity College, 1905-1911 (Box 5)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 4, Trinity College, 1912-1918 (Box 6)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 5, Trinity College, 1914-1926 (Box 7)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 5-A, Trinity College, Class of 1919 (Box 8)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 6, Trinity College, Class of 1920 (Box 9)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 7, Trinity College, Class of 1921 (Box 10)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 8, Trinity College, Class of 1922 (Box 11)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 9, Trinity College, Class of 1923 (Box 12)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 10, Trinity College, Class of 1924 (Box 13)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 11, Trinity College, Class of 1925 (Box 14)
  - Register of Class Grades, No. 12, Trinity College, Class of 1926 (Box 15)
  - Brown Book, Class of 1915 (Box 16)
  - Matriculation Book, 1891-1893 (Box 17)
  - Registration Record, 1901-1915 (Box 17)
  - Admissions Record, 1909-1916 (Box 17)
  - Index to Trinity Park High School Records, undated (Box 17)
  - Registration Book, 1894-1903 (Box 18)
  - Trinity High School, Vol. 1, 1901-1909 (Box 18)
  - Trinity High School, Vol. 2, 1908-1914 (Box 18)
- Subject files, 1946-1988
  The subject files have been divided into two subseries by individual Registrars (either Tuthill or Cahow). The records include reports, studies, correspondence, and memoranda. Additionally, there is a third subseries of unprocessed subject files.
  - Richard L. Tuthill, 1946-1969
    R. L. Tuthill served as University Registrar from 1953 to 1969. The records in this subseries reflect his activities within that office and his participation in local, state, and national organizations. Among the more notable subjects include procedures and policies in student registration and information relating to foreign students at Duke. Others include the Allen Building Takeover, Advanced Placement, and the Conference on Admission and Guidance of African Students (Howard University, 1967). Since the undergraduate admissions responsibility lay with the Registrar's office during Tuthill's tenure, files on admissions are present as well. Tuthill resigned from the office after the Allen Building Takeover (1969) and retired from the University (Professor Emeritus of Geography) eleven years later.
    - Academic Council, 1962-1969 (Box 19)
    - Academic Standards Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 19)
    - Administrative Study Committee, 1959 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: application forms, circa 1955 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: policy (2 folders), 1953-1961 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: procedures, 1951 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: recruitment, 1954-1955 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: statistics (8 folders), 1954-1961 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: studies, 1951-1957 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: Undergraduate Admissions Policy Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 19)
    - Admissions: Woman's College, 1950-1962 (Box 19)
    - Advanced Placement Program (5 folders), 1958-1965 (Box 19)
    - Air ROTC: Tyndall Air Force Base, 1956 (Box 19)
    - Air Science Board, 1953 (Box 19)
    - Allen Building Takeover, 1969 (Box 19)
    - All-University Convocation Committee, 1964 (Box 19)
    - Alumnae Day Morning Forum, 1957 (Box 19)
    - Alumni Association meeting, Lancaster, Pittsburgh PA, 1956 (Box 19)
    - Alumni Association meeting, Greenville SC, 1958 (Box 19)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP): Duke Chapter, 1960-1968 (Box 19)
    - American Council on Education: Committee on Academic Degrees, 1962-1965 (Box 19)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1964-1966 (Box 19)
    - Annual Reports (14 folders), 1954-1969 (Box 20)
    - Association for Childhood Education International: Study Conference, 1959 (Box 20)
    - Association of College Admissions Counselors, 1959-1961 (Box 20)
    - Athletic Department, undated (Box 20)
    - Bulletin publication, 1954-1964 (Box 20)
    - Bureau of Testing and Guidance, 1954-1963 (Box 20)
    - Catalog, 1954-1961 (Box 20)
    - College Entrance Examination Board, 1954-1962 (Box 20)
    - Commencement Committee, 1954-1969 (Box 20)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Changes in the Grading System: plus (+) and minus (-), 1966 (Box 20)
    - Ad Hoc Committee re: Distinguished Professor Seminars, 1964 (Box 20)
    - Committee on Educational Administration, 1962-1968 (Box 20)
    - Committee on Public Education and the Training of Teachers, 1969 (Box 20)
    - Conference on Admission and Guidance of African Students: Howard University, 1967 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: Clark Cahow, 1960-1969 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: Provost R. Taylor Cole, 1966-1968 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: President Edens, 1954-1960 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: Faculty (2 folders), 1955-1967 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: Vice-President Paul Gross, 1954-1960 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence: President Deryl Hart, 1960-1963 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence: Dean Marcus Hobbs, 1959-1963 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence: Alan K. Manchester, 1954-1961 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence: Medical School, 1954-1964 (Box 21)
    - Counselors' Conference, 1960 (Box 21)
    - Deans' Committee, 1962 (Box 21)
    - Diplomas: handling procedures, 1957-1969 (Box 21)
    - Early Decision Plan, 1957-1960 (Box 21)
    - Elementary Education Conference, 1957 (Box 21)
    - College of Engineering Lecture Series: application of computers, 1954 (Box 21)
    - ESSO Education Foundation, 1964-1967 (Box 21)
    - Faculty Committee on Student Concerns, 1969 (Box 21)
    - Faculty statistics, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Foreign Student Committee, 1962-1969 (Box 21)
    - Foreign Student Committee, 1962-1969 (Box 21)
    - Foreign students (3 folders), 1946-1962 (Box 21)
    - Foreign students, faculty, and personnel: directories, 1961-1962 (Box 21)
    - Founders' Day, 1964 (Box 21)
    - Free Academic Senate, 1969 (Box 21)
    - General Motors National Scholarship, 1959-1969 (Box 21)
    - General Motors National Scholarship: steering committee (2 folders), 1960-1962 (Box 21)
    - IBM installation, 1955-1956 (Box 21)
    - Samuel A. Jessup Memorial Scholarship program, 1961-1969 (Box 21)
    - Junior English Examination, 1952-1958 (Box 21)
    - Long Range Planning Committee: 200-level course study, 1962 (Box 21)
    - MacDill Air Force Base, 1957 (Box 21)
    - Methodist Church: questionnaire, 1952-1954 (Box 21)
    - Nagai, Kuniaki, 1967 (Box 21)
    - National Beta Club, 1956 (Box 21)
    - Notices to students, 1956-1957 (Box 21)
    - Office procedures, 1956-1957 (Box 21)
    - Orientation, 1956 (Box 21)
    - Pan American Regional Conference, 1954 (Box 21)
    - Parker Committee, 1959 (Box 21)
    - Permanent mailing list numbers, 1960-1961 (Box 21)
    - Personnel, 1954-1965 (Box 21)
    - Position re-classification project, 1968 (Box 21)
    - Questionnaires, 1954-1966 (Box 22)
    - Recruiting, 1954 (Box 22)
    - Registration: course limits (2 folders), 1954-1961 (Box 22)
    - Registration: College of Engineering: procedures, 1951 (Box 22)
    - Registration: forms, circa 1954 (Box 22)
    - Registration: Graduate School: procedures, 1951 and 1957 (Box 22)
    - Registration: Graduate School: procedures, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Registration: procedures (6 folders), 1953-1960 (Box 22)
    - Registration: student fee payment, 1951 (Box 22)
    - Registration: student helpers, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Registration: Summer session: procedures, 1 951-1953 (Box 22)
    - Registration: Trinity College: procedures, 1951 (Box 22)
    - Registration: Woman's College: procedures, 1951 (Box 22)
    - Religion Department: curriculum, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Report to President, 1954-1961 (Box 22)
    - Routine reports, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Dr. George Van Santvoord, visit to Duke, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Scholarship Selection Committee: Educational Testing Service, 1968 (Box 22)
    - Selective Service, 1951-1968 (Box 22)
    - Social Studies Sub-committee: University Committee on Public Education and Training of Teachers, 1963 (Box 22)
    - Special students, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Statistics: enrollment estimates, 1953-1960 (Box 22)
    - Student averages, 1954-1959 (Box 22)
    - Student organizations: officers, 1954-1955 (Box 22)
    - Student Photographs Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 22)
    - Student records: policy, 1966-1967 (Box 22)
    - Study Abroad Committee (6 folders), 1961-1969 (Box 22)
    - Superior Student Conference, 1959 (Box 22)
    - Transcript Samples removed from grade books, 1948-1952 (Box 22)
    - Travel itineraries, 1959-1960 (Box 22)
    - Tuition increase, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Undergraduate Admissions Policy Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 22)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council, 1954-1963 (Box 22)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council Committee on Admissions, 1953-1959 (Box 23)
    - Undergraduate tuition, 1955 (Box 23)
    - University Calendar, 1948-1963 (Box 23)
    - University Council, 1954-1962 (Box 23)
    - University Council on Research, 1955-1968 (Box 23)
    - University Faculty, 1956-1964 (Box 23)
    - University Religious Council, 1958-1963 (Box 23)
    - University Schedule Committee, 1951 (Box 23)
    - University Schedule Committee, 1956-1972 (Box 23)
    - University Scholarship Committee (2 folders), 1956-1965 (Box 23)
    - Withdrawal studies, 1955-1960 (Box 23)
    - Woman's College: report on dormitory space, 1956 (Box 23)
  - Clark R. Cahow, 1953-1988
    Clark Cahow served as University Registrar from 1969 to 1987. The records in this subseries document the activities of the Registrar's office through correspondence, memoranda, reports, and studies. This subseries also includes records generated as a result of Cahow's service as Director of Undergraduate Admissions and Financial Aid from 1973 to 1978, a position he held concurrently with that of Registrar. The admissions and financial aid material found within this subseries was not necessarily created by the Office of the Registrar but is present due to Cahow's position as head of both offices. Other subjects of note include the University Schedule Committee, the Undergraduate Faculty Council on Arts and Sciences, and University Committees on Admissions and Financial Aid. Cahow is a Professor Emeritus in History.
    - Academic Affairs Committee, 1979 (Box 23)
    - Academic Council, 1973-1974 (Box 23)
    - Academic Council, 1973-1974 (Box 23)
    - Academic Council: Undergraduate Academic Programs subcommittee, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Academic status of Duke: Board of Trustees review, 1976 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: athletes, 1980-1984 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: black admissions, 1982-1983 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: budget (2 folders), 1973-1979 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: calendar, 1980-1984 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: Chancellor's Advisory Committee on Admissions, 1979 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: correspondence (5 folders), 1967-1981 (Box 23)
    - Admissions: correspondence (3 folders), 1982-1986 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: early decision, 1984-1986 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: January admissions, 1982-1984 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: job descriptions, 1974 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: office renovations, 1979-1984 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: policy, 1978-1980 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: policy review and recommendations, 1982-1983 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: publications, 1979-1982 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: recruitment, Texas, 1980-1982 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: recruitment travel itineraries, 1981-1982 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: reports, 1976-1979 (Box 24)
    - Admissions: studies, 1987 (Box 24)
    - African Scholarship Program of American Universities (ASPAU) (2 folders), 1964-1972 (Box 24)
    - Allied Health Professions Conference, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Alumni Scholarship Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 24)
    - Lucien Angbo-Angbo, 1967-1970 (Box 24)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholarship, 1974-1978 (Box 24)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholarship Advisory Committee ( 2 folders), 1978-1988 (Box 24)
    - Athletic policy manual: revisions, 1983 (Box 24)
    - Budget, 1968-1978 (Box 24)
    - Bulletin publication, 1960-1963 (Box 24)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1970-1971 (Box 24)
    - Catalog, 1953-1965 (Box 24)
    - Chancellor's Budget Study, 1982 (Box 24)
    - Commencement Committee: Scheduling of Commencement Events Subcommittee, 1972-1973 (Box 24)
    - Ad Hoc Committee to Consider a B.S. in Health Sciences, 1970 (Box 24)
    - Ad Hoc Committee of Users of Records and Registration via Office of the Registrar, 1970 (Box 24)
    - Computing systems, 1969 (Box 24)
    - Convocation Day, 1965 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence: Colin C. Blaydon, 1981 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence: Deans, 1955-1971 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence: Deans: Woman's College, 1967-1971 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence: Frank T. deVyver, 1962-1969 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence: Faculty (2 folders), 1975-1981 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence: President Douglas K. Knight, 1962-1969 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence: miscellaneous, 1968-1969 (Box 25)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget Management Consultants, 1960-1961 (Box 25)
    - Curriculum Committee: Subcommittee on History (2 folders), 1978-1979 (Box 25)
    - Danforth Apprentice Teaching, 1968-1969 (Box 25)
    - Data processing systems and registration, 1967-1968 (Box 25)
    - Director of Admissions and Financial Aid search, 1974 (Box 25)
    - Duke Endowment, 1980-1982 (Box 25)
    - Duke University Athletic Association (DUAA), 1974 (Box 25)
    - Educational Administration Advisory Group, 1969-1972 (Box 25)
    - Educational Administration Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 25)
    - Educational Facilities Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 25)
    - Educational Facilities Committee: Subcommittee on the Student Union (2 folders), 1970-1974 (Box 25)
    - Educational Testing Service (ETS) interview survey, 1966-1967 (Box 25)
    - School of Engineering: publications, 1973-1974 (Box 25)
    - English 100, 1963-1964 (Box 25)
    - Enrollment projections (2 folders), 1977-1985 (Box 25)
    - ESSO Education Foundation, 1967-1968 (Box 25)
    - ESSO Education Foundation, 1970 (Box 25)
    - Ethridge Fellowship, 1966-1968 (Box 25)
    - Faculty Admissions Review Committee, 1979 (Box 25)
    - Faculty information: including appointments of chairmen and department heads, 1956-1965 (Box 25)
    - Federation proposal, 1970-1971 (Box 25)
    - Financial aid (4 folders), 1972-1978 (Box 25)
    - Financial aid (8 folders), 1978-1985 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: appeals, 1982-1983 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: Basic Education Opportunity Grant program (BEOG), 1978 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: budget study, 1976 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: budgets, 1980-1985 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: college work study program, 1980-1983 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: Educational Savings Accounts, 1981 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: federal programs, 1981-1983 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: federal regulations, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: FISL funds, 1978-1984 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: GSL funds, 1981-1984 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: HEW eligibility, 1982 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: NDSL funds, 1973-1974 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: need-based withdrawals, 1982 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: operation review, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: PLUS loan program, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: policy, 1978-1984 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: proposed budget cuts, 1982 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: Proposed Undergraduate Financial Awards Policy, 1981 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: report: Financial aid in the Eighties, 1979 (Box 26)
    - Financial aid: reports, 1978-1979 (Box 26)